{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Statement: Should India encourage exports, when most things are insufficient for internal use itself?\nArguments:\n\nYes. We have to earn foreign exchange to pay for our imports.\nNo. Even selective encouragement would lead to shortages.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, India can export only the surplus and that which can be saved after fulfilling its own needs, to pay for its imports. Encouragement to export cannot lead to shortages as it shall provide the resources for imports. So, only argument I holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the drugs patented and manufactured in Western countries be first tried out on sample basis before giving licence for sale to general public in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Many such drugs require different doses and duration for Indian population and hence it is necessary.\nNo. This is just not feasible and hence cannot be implemented.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, health of the citizens is an issue of major concern for the Government. So, a product like drugs, must be first studied and tested in the Indian context before giving licence for its sale. So, only argument I holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should India make efforts to harness solar energy to fulfil its energy requirements?\nArguments:\n\nYes, Most of the energy sources used at present is exhaustible.\nNo. Harnessing solar energy requires a lot of capital, which India lacks in.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, harnessing solar energy will be helpful as it is an inexhaustible resource unlike other resources. So, argument I holds. But argument II is vague as solar energy is the cheapest form of energy."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be students union in college/university?\nArguments:\n\nNo. This will create a political atmosphere in the campus.\nYes, it is very necessary Students are future political leaders.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The students union formation shall be a step towards giving to students the basic education in the field of politics. However, it shall create the same political atmosphere in the campus. Thus, both the arguments hold strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should India give away Kashmir to Pakistan?\nArguments:\n\nNo. Kashmir is a beautiful state. It earns a lot of foreign exchange for India.\nYes. This would help settle conflicts.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, India cannot part with a state that is a major foreign exchange earner to it. So, argument I holds strong. Further, giving away a piece of land unconditionally and unreasonably is no solution to settle disputes. So, argument II is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should cottage industries be encouraged in rural areas?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Rural people are creative.\nYes. This would help to solve the problem of unemployment to some extent.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, cottage industries need to be promoted to create more job opportunities for rural people in the villages themselves. The reason that rural people are creative is vague. So, only argument II holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should young entrepreneurs be encouraged?\nArguments:\n\nYes. They will help in industrial development of the country.\nYes. They will reduce the burden on employment market.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, encouraging the young entrepreneurs will open up the field for the establishment of new industries. Thus, it shall help in industrial development and not only employ the entrepreneurs but create more job opportunities for others as well. So, both the arguments hold strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the annual examinations up to Std. V be abolished?\nArguments:\n\nYes. The young students should not be burdened with such examinations which hampers their natural growth.\nNo. The students will not study seriously as they will get automatic promotion to the next class and this will affect them in future.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, neither the students can be burdened with studies at such a tender age, nor can they be left free to take studies casually, as this shall weaken their basic foundation. So, both the arguments follow."}, {"question": "Statement: Should Indian scientists working abroad be called back to India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. They must serve the motherland first and forget about discoveries, honours, facilities and all.\nNo. We have enough talent; let them stay where they want.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, every person must be free to work wherever he wants and no compulsion should be made to confine one to one's own country. So, argument I is vague. However, talented scientists can be of great benefit to the nation and some alternatives as special incentives or better prospects may be made available to them to retain them within their motherland. So, argument II also does not hold."}, {"question": "Statement: Should we scrap the system of formal education beyond graduation?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It will mean taking employment at an early date.\nNo. It will mean lack of depth of knowledge.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, argument I is vague because at present too, many fields are open to all after graduation. However, eliminating the post-graduate courses would abolish higher and specialized studies which lead to understanding things better and deeply. So, argument II is valid."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be an upper age limit of 65 years for contesting Parliamentary/ Legislative Assembly elections?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Generally, people above the age of 65 lose their dynamism and will power.\nNo. The life span is so increased that people remain physically and mentally active even up to the age of 80.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The age of a person is no criterion for judging his mental capabilities and administrative qualities. So, none of the arguments holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should new big industries be started in Mumbai?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It will create job opportunities.\nNo. It will further add to the pollution of the city.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Opening up of new industries is advantageous in opening more employment avenues, and disadvantageous in that it adds to the pollution. So, either of the arguments holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should high chimneys be installed in industries?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It reduces pollution at ground level.\nNo. It increases pollution in upper atmosphere.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Pollution at ground level is the most hazardous in the way of being injurious to human and animal life. So, argument I alone holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Does India need so many plans for development?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Nothing can be achieved without proper planning.\nNo. Too much time, money and energy is wasted on planning.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Before indulging in new development programme it is much necessary to plan the exact target, policies and their implementation and the allocation of funds which shows the right direction to work. So, argument I holds strong. Also, planning ensures full utilization of available resources and funds and stepwise approach towards the target. So, spending a part of money on it is no wastage. Thus, argument II is not valid."}, {"question": "Statement: Should articles of only deserving authors be allowed to be published?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It will save a lot of paper which is in short supply.\nNo. It is not possible to draw a line between the deserving and the undeserving.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, I does not provide a strong reason in support of the statement. Also, it is not possible to analyze the really deserving and not deserving. So/argument II holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should colleges be given the status of a university in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Colleges are in a better position to assess the student's performance and therefore the degrees will be more valid.\nNo. It is Utopian to think that there will not be nepotism and corruption in awarding degrees by colleges.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, at the college level, all the students are assessed according to their performance in the University Exams and not on the basis of any criteria of a more intimate dealings with the students. So, argument I is vague. Also, at this level the awarding of degrees is impartial and simply based on his performance. So, argument II also does not hold."}, {"question": "Statement: Should the prestigious people who have committed crime unknowingly, be met with special treatment?\nArguments:\n\nYes. The prestigious people do not commit crime intentionally.\nNo. It is our policy that everybody is equal before the law.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The Constitution of India has laid down the doctrine of 'equality before the law'. So, argument II holds strong. Also, we cannot judge the intentions of a person behind committing a crime, So, argument I is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Can pollution be controlled?\nArguments:\n\nYes. If everyone realizes the hazards it may create and cooperates to get rid of it, pollution may be controlled.\nNo. The crowded highways, factories and industries and an ever-growing population eager to acquire more and more land for constructing houses are beyond control.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The control of pollution, on one hand, seems to be impossible because of the ever-growing needs and the disconcern of the people but, on the other hand, the control is possible by a joint effort. So, either of the arguments will hold strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should the railways in India be privatized in a phased manner like other public sector enterprises?\nArguments:\n\nYes. This is the only way to bring in competitiveness and provide better services to the public.\nNo. This will pose a threat to the national security of our country as multinationals will enter into the fray.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Privatization would no doubt lead to better services. But saying that this is the 'only way' is wrong. So, argument I does not hold. Argument II also seems to be vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should internal assessment in colleges be abolished?\nArguments:\n\nYes. This will help in reducing the possibility of favouritism.\nNo, teaching faculty will lose control over students.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Abolishing the internal assessment would surely reduce favouritism on personal grounds because the teachers would not be involved in examination system so that they cannot extend personal benefits to anyone. So, argument I holds strong. But it will not affect the control of teaching faculty on students because still the teachers would be teaching them. So, argument II is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the unauthorized structures in the city be demolished?\nArguments:\n\nNo. Where will the people residing in such houses live?\nYes. This will give a clear message to general public and they will refrain from constructing unauthorized buildings.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The demolition of unauthorized buildings would teach a lesson to the unscrupulous builders and also serve as a warning for the citizens not to indulge in such activities in the future. This is essential, as unauthorized constructions impose undue burden on the city's infrastructure. So, only argument II holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be a maximum limit for the number of ministers in the Central Government?\nArguments:\n\nNo. The political party in power should have the freedom to decide the number of ministers to be appointed.\nYes. The number of ministers should be restricted to a certain percentage of the total number of seats in the parliament to avoid unnecessary expenditure.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, there should be some norms regarding the number of ministers in the Government, as more number of ministers would unnecessarily add to the Government expenditure. So, argument II holds strong; Also, giving liberty to the party in power could promote extension of unreasonable favour to some people at the cost of government funds. So, argument I does not hold."}, {"question": "Statement: Should foreign films be banned in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. They depict an alien culture which adversely affects our values.\nNo. Foreign films are of a high artistic standard.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, foreign films depict the alien culture but this only helps in learning more. So, argument I does not hold. Also, the reason stated in argument II is not strong enough in contradicting the ban. So, it also does not hold."}, {"question": "Statement: Is buying things on instalments profitable to the customer?\nArguments:\n\nYes. He has to pay less.\nNo, paying instalments upsets the family budget.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In buying things on instalments, a customer has to pay more as the interest is also included. So, argument I does not hold. Moreover, one who buys an item on instalments maintains his future budget accordingly as he is well acquainted with when and how much he has to pay, beforehand. So, argument II is also not valid."}, {"question": "Statement: Should Doordarshan be given autonomous status?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It will help Doordarshan to have fair and impartial coverage of all important events.\nNo. The coverage of events will be decided by a few who may not have healthy outlook.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the autonomous status of the Doordarshan will be a step towards giving it independence for an impartial coverage. Autonomous status does not mean that the coverage will be decided by a few. So, only argument I holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should adult education programme be given priority over compulsory education programme?\nArguments:\n\nNo. It will also help in success of compulsory education programme.\nYes. It will help to eliminate the adult illiteracy.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, argument I gives a reason in support of the statement and so it does not hold strong against it. The adult education programme needs to be given priority because it shall eliminate adult illiteracy and thus help in further spread of education. So, only argument II is strong enough."}, {"question": "Statement: Should new universities be established in India?\nArguments:\n\nNo. We have still not achieved the target for literacy.\nNo. We will have to face the problem of unemployed but highly qualified people.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, instead of improving upon higher education, increasing the literacy rate should be heeded first. So, argument I holds. Also, more number of universities will produce more degree holders with the number of jobs remaining the same, thus increasing unemployment. So, argument II also holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should non-vegetarian food be totally banned in our country?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It is expensive and therefore it is beyond the means of most people in our country.\nNo. Nothing should be banned in a democratic country like ours.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, restriction on the diet of people will be denying them their basic human right. So, only argument II holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should a total ban be put on trapping wild animals?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Trappers are making a lot of money;\nNo. Bans on hunting and trapping are not effective.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, ban is necessary to protect our natural environment. So, none of the arguments is strong enough."}, {"question": "Statement: Should Government close down loss-making public sector enterprises?\nArguments:\n\nNo. All employees will lose their jobs, security and earning, what would they do?\nYes. In a competitive world the rule is 'survival of the fittest'.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Closing down public-sector enterprises will definitely throw the engaged persons out of employment. So, argument I holds. Also, closing down is no solution for a loss-making enterprise. Rather, its causes of failure should be studied, analyzed and the essential reforms implemented. Even if this does not work out, the enterprise may be privatized. So, argument II is vague,"}, {"question": "Statement: Should government jobs in rural areas have more incentives?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Incentives are essential for attracting government servants there.\nNo. Rural areas are already cheaper, healthier and less complex than big cities. So ? Why offer extra incentives!", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, government jobs in rural areas are underlined with several difficulties. In  lieu of these, extra incentives are needed. So, only argument I holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be a cap on maximum number of contestants for parliamentary elections in any constituency?\nArguments:\n\nYes. This will make the parliamentary elections more meaningful as the voters can make a considered judgement for casting their vote.\nNo. In a democracy any person fulfilling the eligibility criteria can contest parliamentary elections and there should be no restrictions.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, if there were less candidates, the voters would find it easy to make a choice. So, argument I holds. Also, every person satisfying the conditions laid down by the Constitution must be given an opportunity and should not be denied the same just to cut down the number of candidates. So, argument II also holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should so much money be spent on advertisements?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It is an essential concomitant in a capitalist economy.\nNo. It leads to wastage of resources.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the advertisements are/the means to introduce people with the product and its advantages. So, argument I holds strong. But argument II is vague because advertisements are an investment for better gain and not a, wastage."}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the legislators be forced to resign from their profession?\nArguments:\n\nYes. They will be able to devote more time for the country.\nNo, nobody will contest election.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The legislators should surely not be engaged in any other profession because only then will they be able to work with devotion. So, argument I holds. Also, if such a law is enforced, only those people will contest elections who are really prepared to work for the country. So, argument II is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should 'computer knowledge' be made a compulsory subject for all the students at secondary school level?\nArguments:\n\nNo, our need is 'bread' for everyone, we cannot follow western models.\nYes. We cannot compete in the international market without equipping our children with computers.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Nowadays, computers have entered all walks of life and children need to be prepared for the same. So, argument II is strong. Argument I holds no relevance."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be uniforms for students in the colleges in India as in the schools?\nArguments:\n\nYes, this will improve the ambience of the colleges as all the students will be decently dressed.\nNo. The college students should not be regimented and they should be left to choose their clothes for coming to the college.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, after being in strict discipline and following a formal dress code of the school for so many years, the students must be granted some liberty in college life, as they have to take on the responsibilities of life, next. Besides, schools adopt uniforms to take care of the security of the child - an aspect which doesn't matter much in the colleges. So, argument II holds strong. Also, the environment of the college depends on the students' dedication and etiquettes and not on their uniforms. So, argument I is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should India engage into a dialogue with neighbouring countries to stop cross border tension?\nArguments:\n\nYes. This is the only way to reduce the cross border terrorism and stop loss of innocent lives.\nNo. Neighbouring countries cannot be relied upon in such matters, they may still engage in subversive activities.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, peaceful settlement through mutual agreement is the best option, whatever be the issue. So, argument I holds strong. Moreover, the problem indicated in II can be curbed by constant check and vigilance. So, II seems to be vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be a world government?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It will help in eliminating tensions among the nations.\nNo. Then, only the developed countries will dominate in the government.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, a world government cannot eliminate tensions among nations because it will also have the ruling group and the opposition group. Further, the more powerful and diplomatic shall rule the world to their interests. So, only argument II holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should the practice of transfers of clerical cadre employees from government offices of one city to those of another be stopped?\nArguments:\n\nNo. Transfer of employees is a routine administrative matter and we must continue it.\nYes. It involves lot of governmental expenditure and inconvenience too many compared to the benefits it yields.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "It is not necessary that any practice which has been in vogue for a long time is right and it must be continued. So, argument I is not strong. Also, a practice must be continued or discontinued in view of its merits/demerits and not on grounds of the expenditure or procedures it entails. The policy of transfer is generally practised to do away with corruption, which is absolutely essential. So, argument II also does not hold."}, {"question": "Statement: Is paying ransom or agreeing to the conditions of kidnappers of political figures, a proper course of action?\nArguments:\n\nYes. The victims must be saved at all cost.\nNo. It encourages the kidnappers to continue their sinister activities.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the arguments are strong enough. The conditions have to be agreed to, in order to save the life of the victims, though actually they ought not to be agreed to, as they encourage the sinister activities of the kidnappers."}, {"question": "Statement: Should religion be banned?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It develops fanaticism in people.\nNo, Religion binds people together.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Religion binds people together through the name of God and human values. But at the same time it may create differences and ill-will among people. So, either of the arguments holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should India become a permanent member of UN's Security Council?\nArguments:\n\nYes. India has emerged as a country which loves peace and amity.\nNo. Let us first solve problems of our own people like poverty, malnutrition.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A peace-loving nation like India can well join an international forum which seeks to bring different nations on friendly terms with each other. So, argument I holds strong. Argument II highlights a different aspect. The internal problems of a nation should not debar it from strengthening international ties. So, argument II is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should fashionable dresses be banned?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Fashions keep changing and hence consumption of cloth increases.\nNo. Fashionable clothes are a person's self expression and therefore his/her fundamental right.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, imposing ban on fashionable dresses will be a restriction on the personal choice and hence the right to freedom of an individual. So, only argument II is strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should an organization like UNO be dissolved?\nArguments:\n\nYes. With cold war coming to an end, such organizations have no role to play\nNo, In the absence of such organizations there may be a world war.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "An organization like UNO is meant to maintain peace all over and will always serve to prevent conflicts between countries. So, its role never ends. So, argument I does not hold. Also, lack of such an organization may in future lead to increased mutual conflicts and international wars, on account of lack of a common platform for mutual discussions. So, argument II holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be no place of interview in selection?\nArguments:\n\nYes, it is very subjective in assessment.\nNo. It is the only instrument to judge candidates' motives and personality.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, besides interview, there can be other modes of written examination to judge candidates' motives. So argument II is not strong enough. However, the interview is a subjective assessment without doubt. So, argument I holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should family planning be made compulsory in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Looking to the miserable conditions in India, there is no other go.\nNo. In India there are people of various religions and family planning is against the tenets of some of the religions.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Family planning is an essential step to curb population growth. So, argument I holds strong. Also, family planning being against the tenets of some of the Indian religions, it is not necessary to make it compulsory. Instead, it can be enforced by creating public awareness of the benefits of family planning. So, argument II also holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should income tax be abolished in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It is an unnecessary burden on the wage earners.\nNo. It is a good source of revenue.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Income -tax is levied so that every citizen can contribute a share of his earning towards the infrastructural development of the nation. So, argument I seems to be vague. However, income-tax is no doubt a good source of revenue for the government. Hence, argument II holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be a ceiling on the salary of top executives of multinationals in our country?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Otherwise it would lead to unhealthy competition and our own industry would not be able to withstand that.\nNo. With the accent on liberalization of economy, any such move would be counter-productive. Once the economy picks up, this disparity will be reduced.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "In the absence of such a ceiling, the companies would be involved in a mutual competition of salaries, in a bid to attract the most competent professionals. So, argument I holds. Also, the prospects of increase in salary would encourage the officials to perform better in the interest of the company they serve, which would otherwise not be so if a ceiling is imposed. So, argument II also holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should school education be made free in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. This is the only way to improve the level of literacy.\nNo. It would add to the already heavy burden on the exchequer.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Making education free for all is not the only means to ensure literacy. An awareness needs to be aroused for this. So, argument I is vague. Also, such a step would require immense funds and lead to financial drain. So, argument II holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should import duty on all the electronic goods be dispensed with?\nArguments:\n\nNo. This will considerably reduce the income of the government and will adversely affect the developmental activities.\nNo. The local manufacturers will not be able to compete with the foreign manufacturers who are technologically far superior.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Abolishing the import duty on electronic goods shall reduce the costs of imported goods and adversely affect the sale of the domestic products, thus giving a setback to the Indian electronics industry. So, argument II holds strong. Argument I does not provide a convincing reason."}, {"question": "Statement: Should children be legally made responsible to take care of their parents during their old age?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Such matter can only be solved by legal means.\nYes. Only this will bring some relief to poor parents.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Taking care of the parents is a moral duty of the children and cannot be thrust upon them legally, nor such a compulsion can ensure good care of the old people. So, none of the arguments holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be reservation in Government jobs for candidates from single child family?\nArguments:\n\nNo. This is not advisable as the jobs should be offered to only deserving candidates without any reservation for a particular group.\nYes. This will help reduce the growing population in India as the parents will be encouraged to adopt single child norm.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The Government has already made provisions for reservation of jobs for the economically backward sections, which is a must. So, abolishing the practice of reservation altogether has no meaning. Thus, argument I is vague. Also, more reservations would lead to non-recruitment of many more deserving candidates. Besides, such a reservation, if  implemented, will cater to the job requirements of only a small section of population and not a major part of it. So, argument II also does not hold strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should higher education be completely stopped for some time?\nArguments:\n\nNo. It will hamper the country's future progress.\nYes. It will reduce the educated unemployment.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, higher education is not the cause of unemployment. In fact, it has created greater job opportunities. So, argument II is vague. Also, higher education promotes the country's development. So, argument I holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should we scrap the 'Public Distribution System' in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes, Protectionism is over, everyone must get the bread on his/her own.\nYes. The poor do not get any benefit because of corruption.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The Public Distribution System is indeed necessary to provide basic amenities to the economically backward sections of population. So, argument I is vague. Also, if the Objectives of a system are not fulfilled because of corruption, then getting rid of the system is no solution. Instead, efforts should be made to end corruption and extend its benefits to the people for whom it is meant. So, argument II also does not hold,"}, {"question": "Statement: Should India have no military force at all?\nArguments:\n\nNo. Other countries in the world do not believe in non-violence.\nYes. Many Indians believe in non-violence.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, India needs to have military force to defend itself against the threat of other military powers in the world. So, none of the arguments holds strong."}]]}